<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The leper clensed, or, The reduction of an erring Christian being a narrative of Richard Ballamie of Tiverton, his falling off to Anabaptism, and of his returning to the truth : with the causes and occasions of both : wherein he is not onely cleared from the Anabaptists unjust excomunicating of him for leaving them, but their unchristian waies and wildes to deceive are also laid upen / by him published to caution young ignorant Christians against the error of that way.</title>
            <author>Ballamie, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24725</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08448026</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08448026</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41341</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41341)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1245:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The leper clensed, or, The reduction of an erring Christian being a narrative of Richard Ballamie of Tiverton, his falling off to Anabaptism, and of his returning to the truth : with the causes and occasions of both : wherein he is not onely cleared from the Anabaptists unjust excomunicating of him for leaving them, but their unchristian waies and wildes to deceive are also laid upen / by him published to caution young ignorant Christians against the error of that way.</title>
                  <author>Ballamie, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Francis Eglesfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballamie, Richard.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41341:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LEPER CLENSED, OR THE REDVCTION <hi>Of an Erring</hi> CHRISTIAN.</p>
            <p>Being a Narrative of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Ballamie</hi> of <hi>Tiverton</hi> his fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off to <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> and of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to the Truth, with the cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and occaſions of both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein he is not onely cleared from the</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>unjust Excomunicating of him for leaving them, but their unchristian waies and wildes to deceive are alſo laid open.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By him Publiſhed, to caution young ignorant Chriſtians againſt the error of that way.</p>
            <p>Eſaiah 29. 24. <hi>They alſo that erred in ſpirit, shall come to underſtanding; and they that murmured shall learn Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Francis Eglesfield</hi> at the <hi>Mary-gold</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41341:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41341:2"/>
            <head>The Leaper Cleanſed,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may ſeem ſtrange to all that know me, to ſee me in print; and if any that ſee me thus appear, judge that it is me main buſineſſe to vindicate my ſelf, they are miſtaken; I am partly driven to this by the irregular proceedings of thoſe who have judged me as an offender, and yet would not give me liberty to ſpeak for my ſelf: So that I am enforced to ſpeak this way, or to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them by my ſilence; but that which moſt of all prevails with me is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A deſire to give glory to God in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his mercy, who hath opened my eyes and ſhewed me the errour of my way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I judge it my duty, to labour to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all the ſimple and plain hearted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I think it as neceſſary to diſcover the hypocriſie of ſome that lye in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and by cunning inſinuations and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences draw aſide many ſouls to their own loſſe, if not to their deſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41341:3"/>
            <p>It is notoriouſly known to all the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Tiverton,</hi> that I was deeply enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in that way, which is commonly known by the name of Anabaptiſts; yea, ſo far as that I though, I was bound to oppoſe all that diſſented from that way, as being anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian; and ſo zealous was I to promote that intereſt, that I forſook my relations, &amp; left my Fathers houſe, not caring for any ſociety, but ſuch as were for that way; refuſing to joyn in prayer with ſuch as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered from me in that, though otherwiſe godly. Thus I continued for the ſpace of near two yeares, but at laſt God was pleaſed to cauſe me to reflect upon my ſelf and wayes, and by ſome ſpecial providences (of which I ſhall by and by give an account) he made me willing to ſtand upon the waies and ſee, and enquire for the way of the Lord; for untill this time I was ſo filled with prejudice againſt the publick miniſtry, that I refuſed all conferences and debates with any (though offered with never ſo much mildneſſe) concerning the way in which I was: or if I did at any time admit of any, it was to defend and not to examine it: but now God having put ſome check upon my ſpirit; I began to lay things in the ballance, and obſerving another people in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41341:3"/> this place, walking under Ordinances, and joyned with the publick miniſtry; ſuch thoughts as theſe are would come in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. We ſay, we are in the way of God, &amp; they ſay they are in the way of God: May not I all this while be miſtaken? Though I often oppoſed ſuch thoughts as theſe, yet they returned upon me by my obſervation; for I could not but take notice that thoſe I walked withall, were looſer both in their principles and practizes, than thoſe I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented from; I found them ſleight in their thoughts of the Sabbath, and that they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that day rather out of policy than out of conſcience; not ſo much to ſanctifie the name of God, as to keep their hearers from attending the publick Miniſtry: they ſpeak ſleightly of thoſe that walked ſtrictly and cloſely with God in duty; ſaying, that all the Religion of ſuch lay in duties, but theirs was ſpirituall. I further obſerved, that their families were without prayer ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally; their children without inſtruction; and ſurely their conſtant neglect of duties in their families, made me grow very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of mine in private. The conſideration of theſe things, made me begin to enquire whether this were the truth which I profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. From henceforth I reſolved to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41341:4"/> what was objected againſt the way I was in, and to weigh the Arguments I had ſlighted, becauſe I ſaw many ſerious godly people did live in the profeſsion &amp; practice of that which I oppoſed. And upon ſerious inquiring into the Word, and earneſt ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, it pleaſed the Lord to ſatisfie me in the truth: and in particular touching theſe two controverted truths:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Covenant of grace, ſtands now in force to the children of believers under the Goſpell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this is a ſufficient ground by Gods appointment, why the children of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſhould be baptized: this is evident from many ſcriptures in the new Teſtament, which the Anabaptiſts have endeavoured of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to obſcure; I ſhall onely mention one, which was as full to me, <hi>Act. 2. 39. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is to you, and to your children;</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts have laboured to darken this truth, by perſwading the world to believe that children have no right to the Promiſe, till they are actually called, which they would infer from the laſt claim of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Text. But by conſidering I ſaw their miſtake in the Text, (<hi>Call</hi>) hath no relation to children but to them afar off.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41341:4"/>1. Becauſe the children are joyned with their Parents in the promiſe which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire propoſition in the Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If children ſhould be excluded from the promiſe, this could not have comforted the Parents, but have ſadned them, that their children ſhould be the ſame with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. Now here the ſcope of the Text is urged by the Apoſtle for conſolation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If ſo; Then this could not encourage the Parents to ſubmit to theſe under this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration but would have hindred them that their children ſhould be excluded from the promiſe, who ſtood in it for 2000 years before, under the other adminiſtration.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If ſo then, children would be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous in this Text, and ſo the ſpirit of God would be charged with tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tologies, which would be blaſphemy to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The tenſe is changed, the promiſe is to you and your children, in the preſent tenſe; but when he ſpeaks of the call, he ſpeaks in the future tenſe; as many as God <hi>ſhall</hi> call which muſt needs be applied to them afar off, and not to children.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If their interpretation hold good, there would be a very great charge in the extent of the covenant, narrower under the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41341:5"/> Goſpel then it was under the law, and no notice in all the Book of God given of ſuch a change.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If their interpretation be true, then the believing Jews ſhould have loſſe by their repentance, if their children ſhould be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Promiſe, as ſoon as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents had repented.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Then they could have no hope of their children, for hope without promiſe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
            <p n="9">9. If children ſhould be excluded from the promiſe, let any man breathing ſhew me what priviledge the children of repenting parents have above others? Now it is clear the Apoſtle addes children in the Text, to ſhew that they had ſome ſpeciall priviledge above thoſe that were yet uncalled.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Then how could the bleſſing of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> come to the Gentiles according to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 14. which bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> was, I will be a God unto thee, and thy ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Then how can believers be heires ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 29. if their children ſhould be excluded from the promiſe, for the childrens right to the promiſe is a part of the fathers Inheritance (For) the promiſe is to thee and thy ſeed.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41341:5"/>
            <p>Laſtly if children be excluded from the promiſe, it ſeemes the Apoſtle went about rather to deceive his hearers then to inform them; it is very unlikely the Apoſtle would uſe the ſame dialect of the Covenant that was formerly uſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> (I am thy God the God of thy ſeed, the promiſe is to you and your children) if it had been his minde, that children ſhould be excluded, I wiſh that men would with unbyaſed hearts weigh thoſe things, and you ſhould ſee that the children of believers as in the promiſe. Further I obſerve that the promiſe is to be conſidered two wayes.</p>
            <p>1. As it is inviſibly made, ſo it is alone to the Elect.</p>
            <p>As it is viſibly made, ſo it is with viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble profeſſors and their children; whoever is in Covenant in the firſt ſenſe, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fall away. But many may be in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the latter ſenſe, who may after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards degenerate and fall away.</p>
            <p>Here let the impartial Reader take notice that the Covenant, as it is viſibly exhibited, is the ground for Baptiſm; ſeeing the ſubjects of the Covenant internally are known to God alone, this diſtinction of the Covenant is clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 4. where the Apoſtle ſayes, the Covenant <hi>pertains</hi> to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41341:6"/> them, and yet the Apoſtle was in great hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſe for them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Its clear from <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 25. where the Jews are called the <hi>Children of the Covenant,</hi> and yet but few of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally in the Covenant. Its clear from <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 11. where they are called, <hi>Gods own,</hi> which could not be by creation, for ſo all are his own; neither could it be by ſpeciall grace, for ſaith the Text, they rejected Chriſt: Then it muſt needs follow, that there was a viſible Church-covenant or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace viſibly exhibited, that gave them a claim to God.</p>
            <p>In a word this muſt be acknowledged by the Anabaptiſts themſelves, elſe how can they call themſelves a viſible Church of Chriſt, if there be no viſible exhibition of the Covenant to give men ſuch a viſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; for there is no claime to God but by Covenant.</p>
            <p>In this ſenſe we are to underſtand, the children of Believers, in the promiſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaning of the Apoſtle in <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 39. Now this Covenant right, is a ground which God himſelf layes down, why any ſhould be baptized, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 38. he requires baptiſme, <hi>verſ.</hi> 39 ſhewes the reaſon <hi>For the promiſe is to you.</hi> Here I deſire the reader to take notice, how the word of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41341:6"/> depends upon the word of promiſe, and with an inſeparable union and Connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there is between the command and the promiſe, the ſame reaſon alledged by the Apoſtle, why the parent ſhould be Baptized is rendred by the ſame Apoſtle, as a reaſon why the children ſhould be Baptized, (for the promiſe is to you and your Children) nay the very ſame comand expreſſed to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize the one is implied to baptize the other, for if ſome or any to whom the promiſe is made, may not be baptiſed there can be no force in the Apoſtles argument.</p>
            <p>Thus the Lord ſatisfied me about Infant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Being thus far ſatisfied I went to heare the publick Miniſtry, but this comming to the eares of the Anabaptiſts, there came three of their ſociety the next day to me to have an account concerning this thing; I told them if they pleaſe to come at a time appointed I would give them the reaſons of my withdrawing from them; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they came, the preachers &amp; the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipaleſt among them, where I gave them an account of my withdrawing from them, as many of my friends can bear witneſſe, which was as followeth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their denying the children of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41341:7"/> Believers a right to the Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Living in conſtant neglect of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt (<hi>viz.</hi>) ſinging of Pſalms.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For neglecting of Family duty, maintaining it to be a mans liberty, not his duty to pray in his Family.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For denying the power of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate for puniſhing of evil doers: (to wit, Quakers.)</p>
            <p n="5">5. For ſleighting the publick Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>I offered to give them a farther account of my withdrawing from the hypocriſie and wickedneſſe of one <hi>VVilliam Facye,</hi> who is their preſent Paitor, but they refuſed to hear, and deſired I would not caſt dirt to their face; I deſired that they would pleaſe to give an account what they had againſt me; but I could get nothing but this from them (<hi>viz.</hi>) You are withdrawn from us, and have neglected your place amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Then they ſolicited me again to return to them, but ſeeing they could not prevail, they ſummoned me to appear before them ſuch a day. I told them if I might have the liberty to bring ſome friends of mine with me, I would meet with them; this being granted and the day aſſigned, I deſired Mr. <hi>Forteſcue Lowman</hi> Miniſter of the Word in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41341:7"/> 
               <hi>Cadlie,</hi> with ſome other friends to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, whom I found very ready, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly at the time appointed, came with me to their meeting, where were preſent ſome of the ableſt of that party in theſe parts, Both from <hi>Plymouth, Dartmouth, Totnes, Bonytracy, Bompton</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts, whom they had invited to aſsiſt them; and it is remarkable to behold the juſt hand of the Lord, who will not bear with ſinne, nor ſuffer his truth to fall to the ground; aſſoon as we came into their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it pleaſed the Lord to ſtrike ſuch a damp upon their ſpirits, and caſt them into ſuch an hurrey, that not a man among them would engage to juſtifie their proceeding, but one <hi>Thomas Claſſe</hi> (who was not of that ſociety, but a Teacher of a company of them at <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytracy</hi>) in the name of the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, deſired that all ſuch as were not members of their ſociety would withdraw. I told them if my friends ſhould not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with me according to appointment, I would withdraw alſo (knowing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency of being with them alone, when there was no one to teſtifie the plain truth of things) He told me if I would deny the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſt and his Church, I might. Unto whom I replyed; That the authority
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41341:8"/> of Chriſt I did own, but your authority I did deny. <hi>VVilliam Facy</hi> not willing to be laid open, joyned with this motion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired my friends to withdraw: Then Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> told them he had ſomething to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to them before he did withdraw, if they pleaſed, <hi>Thomas Glaſſe</hi> replyed, pray withdraw, for you have nothing to do here. So we withdrew, and one of my friends ſaid, Report no more that we refuſe to give you a meeting: which falſe report they have often ſpread to deceive the ſimple, and to carry on their deſigne by perſwading the ignorant into an opinion, that ſuch as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from them, have nothing to ſay from Gods word to juſtifie their practice.</p>
            <p>The ſame night came <hi>Thomas Glaſſe</hi> (it is worth inquiring, why they ſent not their own Paſtor <hi>VVilliam Facy,</hi> if they were not aſhamed of him or he to look on me) and one of his brethren to my houſe with a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuage from the reſt of the Anabaptiſts, to declare that they had rejected me. Mr. <hi>Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> being preſent, deſired to know by what Rule they walked to reject a man for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dravving upon ſuch juſt and reaſonable grounds, as I had before urged: But <hi>Thom. Glaſſe</hi> refuſed to entertain any conference with him for his ſatisfaction, and told him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41341:8"/> they had nothing to do with him; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked, why they denyed my friends li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to be preſent in their meeting, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicg to appointment, and refuſed to give Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> liberty to propoſe what he had to offer them. <hi>Thomas Glaſſe</hi> brake out in a pettiſh fit, ſaying, That vve had attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to diſturbe them in the worſhip of God, and charged us with abuſing the name of God, and his people with inciviliry, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and want of knowledge; and withall affirmed, that he was imployed by the reſt of his Brethren to tell us ſo: Unto which Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> replyed, If you are imployed by your Brethren to give us ſuch language, pray be pleaſed to return this meſſuage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, That I humbly conceive they have done us the wrong, to appoint ſuch a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with us, and when we came, to deny us liberty to be preſent; and now to ſend ſuch language after us. 1. We did not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb you in your worſhip of God, for we did neither ſee nor hear you about any religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſe when we came, neither did we ſpeak a word till you bid us depart, neither were uncivill with you, for we withdrew according to your deſire. <hi>Tho. Glaſſe</hi> being deſired to ſhew ſome reaſon for giving ſuch ſlanderous words, replied, that he was not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41341:9"/> come to diſpute, but to declare in the name of their Church that they had rejected me, the particulars of my charge, was as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I had withdrawn from their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; and neglected my place amongſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That I had villified ſome of their Brethren, whom I had forgiven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That I had villified ſome of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for denying Magiſtracy, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of family duty, ſinging of Pſalms.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That I had abuſed my father in law.</p>
            <p>Theſe things put together, <hi>Tho. Glaſs</hi> &amp; one more of his Brethren did in the name of the Church, declare me <hi>guilty of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> [You may judge this was a learned aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly that brought this charge to ſuch a concluſion] and they were ſent to tell me they had rejected me.</p>
            <p>Now that you may ſee the irregular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of ſuch as pretend to religion and under that pretence draw away many poor ſoules from thoſe means, which God hath bleſſed for their converſion and edification, to the end ſuch may be warned to take heed, give me leave to anſwer to my charge and I ſhall ſpeake nothing but the plain truth, and let the moderate judge where the guilt lies.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41341:9"/> for withdrawing from them.</p>
            <p>I judge it a great bleſſing, that the Lord hath ſo far opened my eyes as to bring me out from among them, which will eaſily appear if you remember the grounds I have alleadged, and ſhall yet urge from their wickedneſſe as well of practice as principles that I found amongſt them; inſomuch that I wonder how the ſober amongſt them could walk with them hitherto. But this I ſhall ſhew you in anſwer in the ſecond branch of my charge; which is a villifying ſome members which (ſay they) I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given. The occaſion of this charge they bring againſt me is as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVilliam Facy,</hi> their preſent Paſtor walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo diſorderly, his wickedneſſe was ſo great, that they could do no leſs then ſuſpend him: But ſo ſleightly did they deale in the buſineſſe that his ſuſpenſion pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and admition againe, was all within one week; ſhortly after he fained himſelf mad, and began to play prankes with his wife: called for a baſon to let out his bloud, pretending that he would cut his throat, goes to caſt his childe in the fire, which child ſhortly after ſickned and died; ſo much of this I was both an eye and eare witneſſe unto: for his wife came crying to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41341:10"/> me, that ſhe was afraid to abide with him in houſe; gave me a relation of theſe things, deſiring me to come with her to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; when I came I found him on the bed: I asked him how he did, but he gave me no anſwer, after ſome time I had been there, he aroſe and goes from his houſe; this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs committed by him was deemed then by the Anabaptiſts (as was by afterward himſelf acknowledged) to be out of a deſign to get ſome mony from his wife, having mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a widdow which kept certain bills or bonds of debt in ſome friends hands, leaſt he ſhould conſume it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for which the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts ſuſpended him again, and in a little time received him again; wherein I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſatisfied to this day, and in teſtimony of my diſſatisfaction I refuſed to ſit down with them at the Lords table ever ſince. Now they charge me for villifying ſome of their members, when I ſpeak nothing but the plain truth in declaring againſt their ſins and they ſay I have forgiven him, when I were thus unſatisfied in his repentance, and now judge it but fained; for he that could ſo artificially counterfeite madneſſe, could eaſily counterfeite ſadneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He cryes down the publique Miniſtry; for taking of tythes, when as ſhortly after
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41341:10"/> that his Bretheren had admitted him to their Communion and fellowſhip, he tells them, that unleſſe they would engage to give him 80l. by the year he would leave them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is a notorious lyer that makes little conſcience of his word, and hath reported many untruths, touching the publique Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Tiverton,</hi> nay juſtify himſelf in lyes when he is reproved. There was a young man who wrote notes after Mr. <hi>Lowman,</hi> preaching upon the Doctrine of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in <hi>Tiverton;</hi> which notes this young man delivered to one of the Anabaptiſt who gave them to <hi>William Facy,</hi> within three or four dayes after, this young man came to <hi>William Facy</hi> and demanded theſe notes which he plainly and peremtorily denyed ſaying, he had them not. But <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Facy</hi> with drawing the room, the young man eſpies thoſe notes on the table, and takes them into his hand; <hi>William Facy</hi> comes in, and perceiving the notes in his hand takes the notes by force out of his hand, when the young man reported this to ſome of his friends, <hi>William Facy</hi> comes to this young man, and calls him lyer before his maſter (the young man being then a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant;) but the young man produced ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to teſtifie the truth of this matter,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41341:11"/> who was with him at <hi>William Facyes</hi> houſe, and heard him deny the Sermon notes; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> meeting with <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Facy</hi> reproved him for lying: <hi>William Facy</hi> to juſtifie himſelf, tells Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> that the young man had cleared him in this matter before his maſter, which being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined was found a lye. [So here were three lyes, 1. He denies the Notes, 2. He denies that he did deny them, 3. He affirmes that the young man had cleared him, which were all falſe.] Severall untruths hath <hi>William Facy</hi> reported, which upon examination hath plainly and clearly appeared ſo to be; yet they continue him their paſtor.</p>
            <p>Yet they themſelves have given it under their hands, that he is not fit to manage a diſcourſe to vindicate their practice and way in which they now walk. For there was a diſpute appointed between Mr. <hi>Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> &amp; <hi>William Facy,</hi> which was occaſioned by ſome oppoſition from the Anabaptiſts in <hi>Brampton,</hi> where <hi>William Facy</hi> &amp; his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers came and oppoſed Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> in the Pulpit, who entertained ſome diſcourſe with him before the Congregation, and then referred it to a day of publick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute. The queſtion to be debated was (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the infants of believers were in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41341:11"/> But <hi>William Facy</hi> being deſirous to new ſtate the Queſtion, came to Mr. <hi>Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> houſe and in the preſence of ſeverall, <hi>Swore upon the faith of a Chriſtian,</hi> that the Queſtion to be diſcourſed was not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Infants were in Covenant: But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Infants were to be Baptiſed, (where you may ſee, that ſuch as make little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience what they ſay, will make little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience what they ſwear,) Maſter <hi>Lowman</hi> reproving him for ſwearing; told him that the queſtion to be diſcourſed ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven under each others hand; and if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to have the Queſtion ſo ſtated, it ſhould be done: the time and place was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, the Queſtion ſtated, given in Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. The Anabaptiſts willing to wave the buſineſſe, imployed a modeſt man of their own party, one Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Strange</hi> with ſome others of their Brethren, of which <hi>Thomas Glaſſe</hi> was one, to come and treat with Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> in order to wave the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute. Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> deſired to know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their retreat, they told him becauſe <hi>William Facy</hi> was uncapable to manage ſuch an undertaking. Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> asked if they would give it under their hands, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly they did, and ſubſcribed it in the name of the reſt of their Brethren; upon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41341:12"/> which the diſpute was prevented: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>William Facy</hi> is their paſtor.</p>
            <p>I wiſh that the plain hearted among them would but ſeriouſly conſider, whether they can poſſibly expect a bleſſing from heaven, under ſuch a mans Miniſtery, whoſe courſe I have a little hinted to you, and judge you whither I have not cauſe to withdraw where ſuch iniquitie is indulged.</p>
            <p>The third particular of my charge, is for charging ſome of the Anabaptiſts with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying magiſtrates and the neglecting of family duties and ſinging of Pſalms.</p>
            <p>Let me tell you, I do not charge you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe, for thoſe things abound in you at that rate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſeeing you and ſin will not part, you and I muſt part; and though ſome of you are dear to me (whom I truſt the Lord will convince in his due time) yet the Lord Jeſus is nearer and dearer, whoſe communion I muſt, and through grace do prize before yours, had you &amp; I continued it to be feared, the Lord &amp; I ſhould have part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for while I ſat under your miniſtry, I could never find that bleſſing which I have found from that miniſtry you deſpiſe. That tenderneſſe which the Lord wrought upon my Spirit by the publick miniſtry before I came among you, did much decay while I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41341:12"/> continued with you, and therefore tis no finall mercy that the Lord hath brought me from you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For denying the power of Magiſtrates it is notoriouſly known to many good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Tiverton</hi> how you have carped at the Magiſtracy there for executing their power upon ſabbath breakers and quakers, yea you confeſſed, &amp; pleaded it againſt me, as many of my friends can teſtify, when I charged you with it, affirming that Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates had nothing to do with Quakers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For neglect of family duties you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without bluſhing, ſay that I wrong you in charging the neglect of it upon you: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſcious to your ſelves, that many of your families call not upon God, which I can confidently affirm upon my own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall knowledge, when I walked with you beſides when I charged you with it, you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that it was a mans Liberty and not his duty, to pray in his family, as my friends can teſtify who were then preſent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For neglecting to ſing Pſalmes an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt, you never performed this duty in your aſſemblies, but when I charged you with this, you affirmed it to be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ballads, as my friends can teſtify alſo. I come to the fourth and laſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41341:13"/> of my charge for abuſing my father.</p>
            <p>But whether by word or deed, or in what manner you gave me no account; But ſure I am, if I were guilty of ſuch a thing, you never reproved me: I muſt confeſſe that when I walked with you through your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation I took up many hard thoughts, both of my father and mother, becauſe they laboured to convince me of mine errour: yea and I left my fathers houſe upon this very account, as I have hinted before, but through mercy, the Lord hath ſhewed me my evill in ſo doing, yet you were never the people that admoniſhed me all the while I walked with you. But now you act as if you would rejoyce if you could take up any thing to reproach me and ſet variance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the father and the ſon.</p>
            <p>But had I been guilty of every ſyllable of which you charge me with, how can you bring it to Blaſphemy. The truth is <hi>Thomas Glaſſe,</hi> made many ſad ſhifts to mince the matter, when he was deſired to make forth wherein I had been guilty of Blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>But let all modeſt ſober Chriſtians judge, whither that which lies in the bottom be not my diſcovering their wickedneſſe, and withdrawing from them, though I could not in conſcience continue longer with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41341:13"/> them, when God ſaid, Come out from among them; which makes them to forge ſomething againſt me: and let the reader judge where lies the guilt.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given you a brief Narrative of the principalls and practices of theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, having walked with them and tryed them; and likewiſe an account of Gods gracious dealing in bringing me from them, to attend the publick miniſtry, and of their unjuſt proceedings againſt me in this matter.</p>
            <p>If the good Lord make it uſefull for the good of any poor ſoule to undeceive him, and bring him into the way of God, or to prevent any from departing out of Gods way, I ſhall rejoyce, ſo that God may not looſe his glory, nor any of his people looſe their comfort: which if you tender, be ſure to prize, thoſe wayes in which you received the firſt conviction, leaſt you one day lye dovvn in ſorrow for going away from God, and from the ſtriving of his Spirit. Let me ask you that have withdrawn from that Miniſtry; to whom you can ſay, we are your work of the Lord: have you the ſame tenderneſſe, the ſame affections to God, that you once had in former dayes: are not theſe much decayed? O return from whence you are fallen and repent.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41341:14"/>
            <p>And now I ſhall conclude by giving the reader an account of the ſad experience that I have had in two yeares digreſſion from the publique miniſtry in <hi>Tyverton,</hi> which God did at firſt bleſſe to the awakening of my ſoul.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I do not remember that I have had one Conviction under all the ſermons which I heard whilſt I walked with them; But that ſence of my condition which I had before did abate and by little and little, fall away; after I turned my back upon the means which God made uſe of in working upon me. Therefore I beg of all thoſe upon whoſe hearts God is working to take heed of deſpiſing or ſlighting thoſe inſtruments with whom God is preſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I was drawn off by theſe men, when I was in the greateſt probabillity of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving good from the miniſtery that ever I was: For I do remember ſtill the Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which were made upon my ſoul by thoſe truths which I heard from Mr. <hi>Chiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hull</hi> a little before I was thus drawn aſide, which did work mightily to conviction and to reſolution in me, but the devil envying my proſperity, ſent me this Thorn in the fleſh, and their Inſinuations and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did ſo prevaile with me, that I left this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41341:14"/> miniſtry to attend on them; which was but a diverſion from the work of my ſoul and I find that whereas before I had ſomthings of weigh: upon my ſpirit, theſe were ſoon laid aſide, and I had nothing to doe but to diſpute about baptiſme, and to rayle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt miniſters; ſo that my former awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings were turned into drouſineſſe and doating about queſtions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As I found no profit my ſelf by attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their teaching; ſo I obſerved little to any other. Nay it hath been not onely mine but the experience of others, who have conſtantly attended them as long as my ſelf, that there was nothing but deadneſſe of Spirit, to be gained there, which hath at laſt cauſed them to deſert them alſo.</p>
            <p n="4">4 They are very vigilant and watchfull to find out any that are convinced and awakened under the publique miniſtry, and when they begin to ſee things a little dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and confuſedly, they take the advantage of this twilight in which their ſouls are to put off their commodities, where their ſouls have ſome <hi>tenderneſſe,</hi> and yet a great deal of <hi>ignorance,</hi> they are fit to be wrought upon by them for by reaſon of the firſt, they dare not neglect a Command of God, and by reaſon of the ſecond, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41341:15"/> to them that it is neceſſary to be dipt.</p>
            <p>And they effect this eſpecially by theſe means, Firſt ſhewing them very much kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and pretending very great love and bowels of pity to their ſoules, and they ſtand like <hi>Abſalom</hi> in the gate by fair ſpeeches to draw the hearts of people from their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By promiſing them very much peace in their way, and telling how much peace they have found ſince they entred into this way; and this is a very great notice to ſoules, who have ſome troubles accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their awakeings, and indeed there are very few of their hearers or followers trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Spirit, for they want a ſearching Miniſtry. I fear they get ſuch a peace as I did by looſing my conviction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When they ſee that any do incline to them and their way in judgement, they do preſſe them to a ſpeedy ſubmiſſion to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, that they may not have time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate about it, or to goe to the Miniſter, or any chriſtian friends to adviſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let me therefore from my experience, warn all young Chriſtians to watch in this caſe; for know that if the devill cannot keep off the word from your hearts, he will then draw you off, if it be poſſible, from that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41341:15"/> word and Miniſtry which he ſees doth profit you. And doubtleſſe he hath gotten much by this deſigne; And many ſoules will at laſt lament what I now do (<hi>viz.</hi>) that they were ſo ſoon perſwaded to leave the means in which God did vouchſafe to ſtruggle with their ſoules, and if any ſuch Temptation do come in your way, I beſeech you to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate about it, and though it be backt with promiſes of peace; yet enquire whither that which others call peace, may not be more fitly called ſlumber.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I have ſeen how they labour to hold thoſe by policy, whom they have gained by craft; they hinder all that incline to them from hearing any that diſcent from them as much as in them lies, though never ſo godly, Nay though they acknowledge that they have been the Inſtruments of their Converſion. Nay they do abſtaine from all ſociety with Chriſtians that are principalled &amp; ſettled in their judgements, &amp; able to defend them; leaſt any of their weak ones ſhould heare any thing that contradicts their principles: ſo that it is nothing but ignorance, of what is to be ſaid againſt their principles and practiſes, that keeps the greateſt part of their followers to them. Let me therefore beg you, that would know the truth, to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41341:16"/> waigh what is brought againſt, as weld as what is to be ſpoken for your opinion, for it is an argument of weakneſſe and guilt when we ſhun the tryall: The papiſts are Conſcious that their opinions and practices would not ſtand if the Scriptures ſhould be opened to the people, and doubtleſſe many of you do fear what would follow, if your hearers ſhould know what miniſters do or can offer to the people againſt your way. But it is eaſy to keep them to you, who muſt receive your interpretations of Scriptures and no other.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They do preſſe very vigorouſly obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all the commands of God, and in Generals they will ſeem zealous of or God, and holineſſe: But when it comes to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, all their zeal runs out into a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their way; as if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that weight that Dipping is on; But for the mortification of ſin, for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of Religion in Families, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the reſpective duties of their Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; theſe are not minded, ſo that I muſt profeſſe though I have heard them eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile Miniſters as Scribes and Phariſees; yet I never ſaw any Generation of men, that did more reſemble the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees then they in this, in that they laid up
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41341:16"/> their Religion much in litttle things, in certain waſhings, and ſo did theſe: they have more charity many of them for Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and Ranters, then for thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not to the Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not this of all, for as I have ſaid; I believe there is a mixture of godly amongſt them, for vvhoſe ſakes I vvrite theſe things, that they may be vvarned.</p>
            <p>And novv I bleſs the Lord, that he hath brought me back again, and given me a taſt of the ſweetneſſe of the publique Miniſtry in this place: And that I find God meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſoul, and ſtirring a freſh upon my ſpirit; and I cannot but pray and mourn for thoſe that yet remain under the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, with which I was holden a long time: I truſt yet, that the time is comming, that many more of them will ſee the evil of their wayes as I have done; and be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled as I have been; and deſire yet to be more and more before the Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
